BETH: A constructive environment is
an environment where there is not an
overload of sensory stimuli be it visual,
auditory, olfactory or related to space
and an individual with autism has to
feel safe and comfortable to be able
to communicate or interact socially.
Let’s look at some of the issues,
starting with the lighting
is it natural or artificial?
JOE: Lighting plays a large
part in the sensory experiences
of many autistic people.
We now know that fluorescent lights can
be very distracting even to the point
of debilitating for some people because
they can see the lights flickering.
BETH: Is the environment
cluttered or minimalist.
Many people with autism need
space around them and feel
overwhelmed by crowds or clutter.
They can feel hemmed in by corridors
and need to know there is a quick
escape route or a place they can
remove themselves to which is calmer.
JOE: Individuals with Autism can
become overwhelmed by too much
visual information to process.
Patterns can be distracting
and overwhelming and can
even cause visual distortion.
BETH: What about sounds
internal or external?
Are there any regular ‘external’
sounds, such as traffic, children
playing or construction noise?
Are there regular ‘internal' sounds,
such as ticking clocks, machines
humming, music or radio noise?
JOE: Is it possible to
reduce these sounds?
Many individuals with autism
can hear sounds at many decibels
above those others can hear.
They hear sounds that are further away
and the intensity can often be deafening.
BETH: Are there any strange smells?
There may be smells from outside
permeating through the walls
or from within such as cleaning
products, perfumes or foods.
Some people with autism find smells
so overwhelming that they cause
extreme nausea and some can even
smell something for a long time after
it has been removed from the room.
JOE: To focus on social interaction and
communication many individuals with autism
need to have reduced sensory distractions
to be able to listen to conversations,
to respond appropriately, keep calm and
relate to what is being said, rather
than be distracted to some extent or in
extremes suffering from sensory overload.